So we are back. We're a bit behind, but let's really focus
and catch up. Officially today's דף Daf is סז Samech-Zayin 67. We
are on סו עמוד ב. Samech-Vav Amud-Bet. 24th of the עומר Omer
by the way. And we actually pick up two lines from the
bottom of סו עמוד א. Samech-Vav Amud-Aleph. The last two words on
סו עמוד א. Samech-Vav Amud-Aleph. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Okay, now we
can turn to סז. Samech-Zayin. סו עמוד ב. Samech-Vav Amud-Bet. Okay, מנא
אמינא לה. Mena amina lah. Where do I know this from? And
this is the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava about whether
we
say that you need two witnesses not only to make a קידושין
Kiddushin happen, to make a גט Get happen, but even as a
standard of proof about personal status. And one witness is not enough,
even if that witness is not contradicted. אביי Abaye said one witness
would be enough. רבא Rava said it is not. אין דבר שבערוה
פחות משניים Ein davar she-be'erva pahot mi-shenayim translates into ways according to
רבא, Rava, you need two witnesses to make it happen, and you
need two witnesses to prove that it happened. Okay. So מנא Mena
and this is not just about גט Get and קידושין. Kiddushin. For
example, some of the discussions were about whether a woman was taken
captive and whether that would make her אסור Assur to a כהן.
Kohen. Whether a woman committed adultery and that would make her אסור
Assur to her husband. Okay, so רבא Rava says, מנא אמינא לה,
Mena amina lah, where do I know this that you need to
have two witnesses? דתנן, De-tenan, we taught in the משנה. Mishnah. אמר
רבי שמעון. Amar Rabbi Shimon. It's interesting that it says דתנן. De-tenan.
Yeah, it's a משנה Mishnah somewhere. The side says it's also a
תוספתא. Tosefta. All
right, anyway. אמר רבי שמעון. Amar Rabbi Shimon. מעשה במגורה של דיסקים.
Maaseh be-megurah shel Diskim. There was a story in a certain well
or a body of water in this place called דיסקים. Diskim. Or
רש"י Rashi says it's either the name of a person or the
name of a place. Okay, ביבנה, Be-Yavne, in Yavne, שהיתה עומדת בחזקת
שלמה. She-hayta omedet be-hezkat shlemah. People assumed that there was enough water
in it, as it was a כשר Kosher מקוה. Mikvah. ומדדו, U-madadu,
and then after a few months, some חכם Hacham decided to measure
it. ונמצאת חסרה, Ve-nimzet haserah, and it didn't have 40 סאה. Se'ah.
So כל טהרות שנעשו על גביה, Kol taharot she-naasu al gabeah,
what's the status with everything that's been used in that מקוה, Mikvah,
all the vessels that have been dunked in the
מקוה Mikvah from the last time it was checked when we knew
it was שלם, Shalem, and then three months later when we checked
it and we found out that it was not שלם? Shalem? So
it obviously didn't happen the first day after day one after we
measured it three months ago. So when do we assume that it
actually went under 40 סאה? Se'ah? So רבי טרפון... Rabbi Tarfon... so
אמר רבי טרפון... Amar Rabbi Tarfon... well wait, היה רבי טרפון מטהר.
Hayah Rabbi Tarfon mitaher. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says we can assume
it remained שלם Shalem until the last possible minute, until the minute
that we measured it. And anything prior to that is okay. ורבי
עקיבא מטמא. Ve-Rabbi Akiva metame. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no,
everything that's been done since the last time we measured it is
טמא, Tame, it maybe not was שלם.
Shalem. Well, exactly. So let's see.
דאמר רבי טרפון, De-amar Rabbi Tarfon, מקוה זה בחזקת שלם הוא עומד.
Mikvah zeh be-hezkat shalem hu omed.
What do you mean? We have a principle of חזקה. Hazakah. It
had a status of being, of being כשר, Kosher, of being a
full amount. מספק אתה בא לחסרו. Mi-safek atah ba le-hasro. You're saying,
well, I don't know, maybe it may we don't know when it
became חסר, Haser, when it became פסול. Pasul. So we have to
say maybe it became פסול Pasul way at the beginning. You're not
allowed to do that. אל תחסרנו מספק. Al tehasrenu mi-safek.
Your doubt of when it became חסר Haser does not override its
status quo of being שלם. Shalem. That's a principle of חזקה. Hazakah.
The whole point of a חזקה Hazakah is something has a status
quo. If you don't know when that status quo changed, then you
assume that it retains the status quo. So until the last possible
minute when you have evidence that it changed, you assume that it
was שלם. Shalem. Yes, I know. Yes. That is the general principle
of חזקה. Hazakah. That's a very reasonable position. אמר רבי עקיבא. Amar
Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, but you're forgetting that something
else here has a חזקה. Hazakah. אדם זה בחזקת טמא הוא עומד.
Adam zeh be-hezkat tame hu omed.
Any person, man, woman, who used the מקוה, Mikvah, before they went
into the מקוה, Mikvah, their status quo was that they were טמא.
Tame. מספק אתה בא לטהרו. Mi-safek atah ba le-taharo. You say, well,
I don't know if he became טהור. Tahor. Maybe did his status
change and he became טהור? Tahor? That depends if he was טובל
Tovel in a כשר Kosher מקוה. Mikvah. אל תטהרנו מספק. Al tetahrenu
mi-safek. You can't change his status if you don't know for sure
that the מקוה Mikvah was כשר. Kosher. So it's a really good
question, like which one do you go by? So אמר רבי טרפון.
Amar Rabbi Tarfon. משל לעומד ומקריב על גבי המזבח. Mashal le-omed u-makriv
al gabei ha-mizbeah.
Let's try to analogize it since we can't really to there's no
way here to figure out which one to tip, whether you go
by the person or the מקוה. Mikvah. Let's look at an analogy.
Let's say you had a person, a כהן, Kohen, who was standing
and being מקריב Makriv קרבנות. Korbanot. ונודע שהוא בן גרושה או בן
חלוצה. Ve-noda she-hu ben grushah o ben halutzah.
And then he was informed, somebody discovered that his mother was divorced
before being married to the father, and that he's a חלל. Halal.
שעבודתו כשרה. She-avodato ksherah. When that happens, we say that nevertheless, his
עבודה Avodah is כשרה Ksherah until that point. After that point, it's
not good. Now, of course, that's a really bad analogy because then
we know that he was פסול Pasul before, right? So logically, of
course, his עבודה Avodah should have been פסול. Pasul. The גמרא Gemara
is going to quote a פסוק Pasuk later on to show us
that actually we can say the עבודה Avodah is כשרה Ksherah even
though we know that he was 100 percent, now that we have
this information, he was a חלל Halal earlier. So that's like a
special גזירת הכתוב Gzeirat ha-katuv that That he was פסול Pasul before,
right? So and logically of course his עבודה Avodah should have been
פסול. Pasul. The גמרא's Gemara going to quote a פסוק Pasuk later
on to show us that actually you know that actually we can
say the עבודה Avodah is כשר Kasher even though we know that
he was a hundred percent now that we have this information he
was a חלל Chalal earlier. So that's like a special גזירת הכתוב
Gezeras Hakasuv that he only invalidates the עבודה Avodah from the moment
we know forward. It seems not really at all relevant to a
question of trying to determine when something happened in the past. Okay?
It's somewhat like the question about you know what happens if you're
reading a ספר תורה Sefer Torah and you find that it has
a פסול Psul and the פסול Psul that did not just happen
now, it's because there's an extra word written in it, okay, or
a whole word is missing. So you actually you don't go back
and re-read the עליה Aliyah but that has to do with other
issues, that has to do with the fact that we can rely
on certain positions בדיעבד B'dieved that you don't need a כשר Kasher
תורה Torah for קריאת התורה. Krias Hatorah. Okay?
But here anyway you don't re-read the עליה, Aliyah, you just finish?
What I'm not going to go into the details but basically correct.
I mean it depends on the circumstances. Yes, but basically that's correct,
won't go into I shouldn't have brought that up, now you're going
to ask me the specifics about that. So anyway
but anyway okay but but anyway
so there are some times you don't have to go back and
re-do it but it's not because you assume it wasn't a problem
until now, there's other reasons. But nevertheless this is the analogy he's
making. So he says, ah, you see in that case we say
it's כשר Kasher moving forward. You know, maybe he's also sort of
pointing out the, you know, maybe there's a subtext here about the,
you know, about the sort of policy consequences. Right? Imagine the policy
consequences if a כהן Kohen at the age of 70 found out
he was a בן גרושה. Ben Grusha. What are you going to
do, send out recall notices to everybody from the last 50 years?
Right? So there's clearly like, you know, even though we have to
base it on a פסוק, Pasuk, we do base it on but
there's a reason why you know we can't retroactively invalidate everything he's
done. So think about the same thing about the מקוה. Mikvah. What
are you going to do, you know, everybody you know women have
been with their husbands since then, people have been eating תרומה Terumah
all this type of stuff, now you're going to say everything you've
been doing the last three months is invalid? So maybe that's a
little bit of the analogy like the sort of policy societal realities
should push us to go by the חזקה Chazakah that the מקוה
Mikvah was כשר Kasher even though again here it's not an issue
of חזקה. Chazakah. So that's what רבי טרפון Rebbi Tarfon says. Okay.
אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rebbi Akiva, אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar
Rebbi Akiva, so רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said back no, משל למה
הדבר דומה? למקום לבא מזה, Mashal l'ma hadavar domeh? L'makom l'ba mizeh,
we're going to compare it to a כהן, Kohen, let's compare it
to a כהן Kohen and who was offering קרבנות, Korbanos, ונודע שהוא
בעל מום V'nodah shehu Ba'al Mum
and here if it turns out that he had a blemish, שעבודתו
פסולה, She'avodaso Pesulah, it's invalid, which is like a little strange, you
would have thought that the you know knowing that you're a חלל
Chalal is a more fundamental פסול Psul than a בעל מום Ba'al
Mum which seems less about fundamentally about identity. And nevertheless the הלכה
Halacha is we only have a פסוק Pasuk for the case of
a חלל Chalal that it's not a problem what he did in
the past if it was in ignorance, but with a בעל מום
Ba'al Mum it actually is פסול Pasul what he did in the
past. So if you're making an analogy to that case...
when he has a מום Mum now
and we realize that he always had the מום, Mum, we just
didn't know about it, right? Okay, so...
what if it was a ספק? Safek? Then it's even a better
proof for רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. Okay, but nevertheless he's saying both
those cases presume that it was around before, but you know, but
there's one case there's a הלכה Halacha that you don't, you know,
you're not concerned about the past, and in this case the הלכה
Halacha is you are concerned about the past.
Let's say he broke his... let's say he went to the doctor
and he found that his arm was broken. Yeah. So how far
back do you go?
No,
well that's, okay, that would then be the debate of רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rebbi Tarfon if you didn't know how
far back to go. But yeah I mean but right now we're
even discussing a case where it's, again, not an exact analogy, but
you found out and you knew for sure before, and how much
does that change things? Okay.
אמר רבי טרפון, Amar Rebbi Tarfon, אתה דמיתו לבעל מום ואני דמיתיו
לבן גרושה או לבן חלוצה. Atah demiso l'ba'al mum v'ani dimisiv l'ben
grusha o l'ben chalutza. You made the analogy to a כהן Kohen
with a מום Mum and I made the analogy to a כהן
Kohen who was a בן גרושה, בן חלוצה. ben grushah ben chalutzah.
נראה למי דומה. Nireh l'mi domeh. Let's, great, let's try now, maybe
we have something to work with. Let's try to figure out which
case our מקוה Mikvah case is more similar to, even though as
pointed out it's not really similar to either because in the מקוה
Mikvah case there's a ספק Safek and here there isn't a ספק.
Safek. Anyway, אם דומה לבן גרושה ולבן חלוצה נדוננו כבן גרושה וכבן
חלוצה. Im domeh l'ben grusha u'l'ben chalutza nidonenu k'ben grusha u'k'ben chalutza.
If it's like the בן גרושה Ben Grusha, case, then if it's
more similar to that, we'll apply that law. אם דומה לבעל מום
נדוננו כבעל מום, Im domeh l'ba'al mum nidonenu k'ba'al mum, and if
it's more similar in terms of its you know relevant features to
the בעל מום Ba'al Mum case, we'll apply the בעל מום Ba'al
Mum הלכה Halacha and we'll say that retroactively it is a problem.
Okay, good. Let's talk about that now. התחיל רבי עקיבא לדון. Hischil
Rebbi Akiva ladun. So let's, so רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said, okay,
let's make the comparison. מקוה פסול ביחיד ובעל מום פסול ביחיד. Mikvah
pasul b'yachid u'ba'al mum pasul b'yachid. ואל יוכיח בן גרושה ובן חלוצה
שפסולו בשנים. V'al yochi'ach ben grusha u'ben chalutza she'psulo b'shnayim. So a
מקוה Mikvah is פסול, Pasul, you know,
an individual can come and say "Hey, I checked it and it's
got a מקוה," Mikvah, I mean it doesn't have enough, and we
would believe him. Normally עד אחד נאמן באיסורין, Ed echad ne'eman b'issurin,
you believe an individual testimony. Similarly if a בעל מום Ba'al Mum
comes and says, you know, if somebody says "Hey I saw this
כהן," Kohen, or this כהן Kohen testifies himself "I have a מום,"
Mum, that would be accepted. As opposed to the question of בן
גרושה, בן חלוצה, ben grushah ben chalutzah, because that's a personal status
issue having to do with ערוה, Ervah, right, and with sex and
with personal status. That requires two witnesses. This is why we're bringing
this whole discussion in. Okay, so therefore it's of a different nature.
Okay, now it's interesting, is that just haphazard that it's different or
is that really relevant to his point? Right, so... but we can,
we'll get back to that in a minute. But let's just say,
so therefore to me it's more similar to the בעל מום Ba'al
Mum and therefore it should be retroactively a problem. Okay, ולא הכי
בן גרושה ובן חלוצה שפסולה מאחרים, V'lo Hachi Ben Grusha v'Ben Chaluza
she'psula m'acherim, other people have to testify and therefore it's less relevant.
Okay, and it seems that the analogy is if you want to
say that's just not haphazard, you know, oh look, I found a
point of comparison, but that it's relevant to the discussion, the point
is is that like if it's easier to establish that something is
a problem, you have a lower threshold needed to establish it's a
problem, to establish that there's a מום, mum, to establish that there's
not enough water in the מקוה, mikvah, then that means that we're
more prepared to assume, to apply that status to it halakhically, to
halakhically recognize that status. So here where there's a question when did
it become חסר chasar and you have the חזקה chazaka of the
person against the חזקה chazaka of the מקוה, mikvah, well in general
we're more prepared and to say that
we'll acknowledge that the מקוה mikvah is חסר. chasar. So therefore that's
what we should say and we should say that everything in the
past is a problem.
אמר ליה רבי טרפון, Amar lei Rabbi Tarfon, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
said,
עקיבא כל הפורש ממך כפורש מן החיים. Akiva, kol haporesh mimcha k'poresh
min hachayim. Anybody who separates from you is who separates from life.
It's sort of like the whole thing about the fish on the
land, right? So anyway, so okay, so anyway so it's funny, like
hey, like that was it, that won the case, like you were
waiting for רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon to do a comparison in the
other direction. Anyway, fine. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says, he gave up
pretty, yeah exactly. האי בעל מום שפסולה ביחיד היכי דמי? Hai Ba'al
Mum she'psula b'yachid heichi dami? What's the case of a בעל מום
Ba'al Mum that one person can testify? Now the גמרא Gemara is
talking, this is why we brought it in, to prove that a
personal status בן גרושה ובן חלוצה Ben Grusha v'Ben Chaluza needs two.
Okay, so האי בעל מום שפסולה ביחיד היכי דמי? Hai Ba'al Mum
she'psula b'yachid heichi dami? What does it mean that one person can
testify according to בעל מום? Ba'al Mum? אי דקא מכחיש ליה, Ei
d'ka machish lei, if the guy is denying it, no you're lying,
I'm not a בעל מום, Ba'al Mum, מי מהימן? mi meheiman? We
wouldn't believe the עד. ed. אלא דשתיק, Ela d'shatik, it must be
that the guy is not contesting it, and therefore we believe one
by a בעל מום, Ba'al Mum, but then the comparison is if
the בעל מום Ba'al Mum is a case of one without being
contested,
ודכוותיה גבי בן גרושה ובן חלוצה דשתיק. ud'chavtei gabi Ben Grusha u'Ben
Chaluza d'shatik. So then
מי מהימן?
mi meheiman? What, meaning if the guy who has the מום mum
is מכחיש machish this one עד? ed?
Yes, then the עד ed wouldn't be believed.
But isn't this an objective thing?
We're going to get to that. Okay, fine, yes, we're going to
get to that, Michael, hold off, everything you're about to ask is
coming up. Okay, but the first what we want to prove is
what רבא Rava is trying to prove is that by personal status
we would not believe one עד ed even uncontested. So he says,
and I'll show it to you because we say a בעל מום
Ba'al Mum works with one and בן גרושה ובן חלוצה Ben Grusha
Ben Chaluza two, but presumably the בעל מום Ba'al Mum with one
is uncontested because if it was contested we wouldn't believe it. So
even though we're dealing with one עד ed uncontested, we say בן
גרושה ובן חלוצה Ben Grusha Ben Chaluza one עד ed is not
enough, you need two. ודכוותיה גבי בן גרושה ובן חלוצה דשתיק, ud'chavtei
gabi Ben Grusha u'Ben Chaluza d'shatik, the guy is not contesting it,
וקתני מקוה פסולה ביחיד ובעל מום פסולה ביחיד ואילו בן גרושה ובן
חלוצה שפסולה בשנים. u'katni mikvah psula b'yachid u'Ba'al Mum psula b'yachid v'ilu
Ben Grusha u'Ben Chaluza she'psula b'shnayim. And nevertheless it says even though
presumably we're dealing with a case that uncontested testimony of
an עד אחד, ed echad, by בן גרושה ובן חלוצה Ben Grusha
Ben Chaluza you still need two. So you see when it comes
to an issue of personal status you need two witnesses and one
uncontested witness is not sufficient. That's רבא's Rava's proof. And אביי Abaye
says back what Michael was going to say. ואביי אמר, V'Abaye amar,
no, לעולם דקא מכחיש ליה. l'olam d'ka machish lei. No, the guy
is contesting the עד אחד ed echad who says he's a בעל
מום. Ba'al Mum. So then why do we believe
the בעל מום? Ba'al Mum? Because the, I mean not the בעל
מום, Ba'al Mum, why do we believe the עד אחד? ed echad?
So then you'd say why would we believe the עד אחד ed
echad if the כהן kohen is contesting it? דאמר ליה שלח אחוי,
d'amar lei shlach achvei, because the עד אחד ed echad says, you're
telling me you're not a בעל מום? Ba'al Mum?
Strip and let's see. Okay, so that's what שלח shlach means, שלח
shlach actually can be a medical word which means like to strip.
Okay, and show, demonstrate. Okay, so you're telling me, I say I
saw you got a מום mum on your side there, you're denying
it, let's, if you want us to believe you, strip. Okay, so
therefore in that case actually if it was, we would believe the
עד אחד ed echad even if it was contested as long as
the guy was refusing to show. והיינו דקתני מקוה פסולה בגופה בעל
מום פסולה בגופה. v'hainu d'katni mikvah psula b'gufa Ba'al Mum psula b'gufa.
Did we skip that line?
We, before you did, oh I'll try to,
you were trying to tell me that? Need to tell me when
you're not asking a question, you're just saying I skipped something. Okay,
I skipped down to, okay, to the דבר אחר, davar acher, I
apologize. Okay, so before the כל הפורש ממך כפורש מן החיים, kol
haporesh mimcha k'poresh min hachayim, I'm sorry, go back, it's about five
lines above the מתניתין matnitin in רש״י. Rashi. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva had two ways of comparing it to the what do you
call it, to the בעל מום. Ba'al Mum. One was a בעל
מום, Ba'al Mum, it's only an עד אחד ed echad suffices and
with בן גרושה ובן חלוצה Ben Grusha v'Ben Chaluza you need two
עדים. edim. And then the דבר אחר, davar acher, I just, so
going back, jumping back here, another thing, another way of comparison, מקוה
פסולה בגופה בעל מום פסולה בגופה. mikvah psula b'gufa Ba'al Mum psula
b'gufa. The מקוה mikvah the problem is in the מקוה, mikvah, there's
not enough water, the בעל מום Ba'al Mum the problem is on
his body, ואילו בן גרושה ובן חלוצה v'ilu Ben Grusha v'Ben Chaluza
and those are different than the בן גרושה ובן חלוצה Ben Grusha
Ben Chaluza case שפסולה מאחרים she'psula m'acherim that that problem comes outside
of him, it's what his parents did. And then
אמר ליה רבי טרפון. amar lei Rabbi Tarfon. So he had two
ways of comparing it to the בעל מום. baal mum. Number one,
בעל מום baal mum עד אחד ed echad is enough and same
with the מקוה, mikvah, and number two, בעל מום baal mum the
problem is in the body of the person or the body of
the מקוה mikvah as opposed to בן גרושה בן חלוצה. ben grushah
ben chalutzah So the גמרא Gemara now says, okay, so back to
where we were. So אביי Abaye was saying, no, that idea that
you would believe an עד אחד ed echad by a בעל מום
baal mum and not by בן גרושה בן חלוצה, ben grushah ben
chalutzah? that is a contested עד אחד. ed echad. And the reason
we believe him by a בעל מום baal mum is because if
it's not true, let the guy show it. Okay, and then back
to the גמרא, Gemara, דהיינו דקתני, dehaynu de'tani, I'm sorry to be
jumping back and forth, but back to where we were, about eight
lines before the lines get start to get wide, okay, where it
says שלח אחזי, shlach achzi, אמר ליה שלח אחזי. amar lei shlach
achzi. Okay, go strip. Okay, so the yes, אביי Abaye says we
are dealing with a contested עד אחד. ed echad. But nevertheless, we
believe him because he can tell the כהן, Kohen, if you're telling
the truth, strip. דהיינו דקתני מקוה פסולה בגופה ובעל מום פסולה בגופו
ויוכיח בן גרושה ובן חלוצה שפסולו מאחרים. dehaynu de'tani mikvah psulah begufah
u'baal mum psulah begufo v'yochiach ben grushah u'ben chalutzah she'psulo me'acherim. So
that's exactly the reason he's saying by a by a בעל מום
baal mum we believe a contested עד אחד, ed echad, but by
a בן גרושה בן חלוצה ben grushah ben chalutzah, we don't believe
a contested עד אחד ed echad because there's nothing to show. How
you gonna prove whether you are or aren't a בן גרושה בן
חלוצה? ben grusha ben chaluza, Right? If it's on the body, we
can say, show. If you're if I'm the עד אחד ed echad
says, if I'm lying, show me otherwise. But by the בן גרושה
בן חלוצה, ben grusha ben chaluza if he's contested, we won't accept
the עד אחד, ed echad, right? Because if I'm lying, the there's
there's nothing to be demonstrated. All right, so that's why if it's
a contested, you need two. Okay, so is that is that sort
of clear, right? The question here is
we've
got the two עדים, eidim, okay, by the בן גרושה. Ben Grusha
Why'd you do that? I don't know. All right, anyway, here's the
case of the בן גרושה Ben Grusha, and we have the two
עדים eidim and we have the one עד. ed. Here are the
עדים eidim and we have the one עד ed by the בעל
מום. baal mum. Okay, yeah, we can have him that he's got
some blemish on him and that he's fighting. Okay, so the point
was like this: we need two in this case and one in
this case. So the גמרא Gemara says, well, presumably when one works,
it's when he's uncontested. That's what רבא Rava says because we normally
wouldn't believe a contested עד. ed. And even though one works uncontested,
one uncontested does not work by בן גרושה. ben grushah. So you
see that by personal status, an uncontested עד ed does not work,
you need two עדים. eidim. That's רבא's Rava proof. And אביי Abaye
says, no, here he is being contested. Okay, oh, I can't do
it anyway. He is being contested. Here, we'll just draw that they're
arguing. Okay, anyway, he is being contested, okay, he is being contested,
but we still believe the עד ed because if you're telling the
truth, show us. But that and that's why we don't believe by
a בן גרושה ben grushah because if he's being contested, then there's
nothing that shows the עד ed is telling the truth, there's nothing
to demonstrate. Right, here if he's refusing to demonstrate, to to show
us, then we know that the עד ed is telling the truth.
Here, it's just he said, he said. There's, you know, there's no
so then we wouldn't believe it. So in a case of being
contested, we need two עדים eidim in this case. Okay, but אביי
Abaye is saying we only need two עדים eidim because it's contested.
If it was uncontested, we would accept it even in a personal
status issue.
A בעל מום baal mum presumably depends upon like what kind of
מום mum it was, meaning like if it's an internal thing, it's
like, you know.
Yeah, internal thing is not a מום. mum. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like it might be a טריפה, tereifah, not a מום.
mum. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so it remains
unproven whether we whether we're talking about a contested עד ed or
not a contested עד ed and whether a case of personal status,
we would believe an uncontested עד ed or would we always need
two עדים. eidim. Now the גמרא Gemara just wraps up the issue
about the כהן. Kohen. The גמרא Gemara says like this, okay we
don't
well, right, we haven't proven it. Okay,
בן גרושה ובן חלוצה עבודתו כשירה מנלן, ben grushah u'ben chalutzah avodato
ksheirah minalan, how do we know this idea that a כהן Kohen
who is discovered to be a בן גרושה, ben grushah. his עבודה
avodah is still כשרה, kosher, everything he did until that point? אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל דאמר קרא, amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel d'amar
kra, the פסוק pasuk says, והיתה לו ולזרעו אחריו. v'haytah lo ul'zaro
acharov.
Right, by פינחס, Phinehas, it should be for him and his future
seed ברית כהונת עולם. bris kehunas olam. בין זרע כשר בין זרע
פסול, ben zera kasher ben zera pasul, זרעו zaro means any of
his descendants, or male descendants, whether כשר kasher or בין זרע פסול.
ben zera pasul. So it'll be this idea that he has a
status of כהן Kohen even if it turned out that he was
a חלל, challal, which is kind of shocking because a חלל challal
you feel fundamentally doesn't have the קדושת כהונה. kedushas kehunah. אבוה דשמואל
אמר, avuh d'Shmuel amar, מהכא, me'hacha, ברך ה' חילו ופועל ידיו תרצה.
bareich Hashem cheilo u'poal yadav tirtzeh. This is by like the לוי,
Levi, bless his service strength. So what does that mean? And the
act of his hands, and תרצה tirtzeh by the way, רצון ratzon
by קרבנות, korbanot, לרצון להם לפני ה'. leratzon lahem lifnei Hashem. So
חז"ל Chazal read this very much in the context of קרבנות korbanot
and פועל ידיו poal yadav bringing מקריב makriv the קרבן, korban, and
it's ברך ה' חילו, bareich Hashem cheilo, אפילו חולין שבו. afilu chullin
she'bo. He used the חילו, cheilo, it's a play on words, even
if it turns out that he doesn't have קדושה, kedusha, even if
it turns out that he's a חלל. challal. תרצה, tirtzeh, only until
that point.
Then no longer, obviously, obviously.
So we read it in that context, when we were ignorant of
it, until the point that we found out.
רבי יוחנן אמר מהכא ובאת אל הכהן אשר יהיה בימים ההם. Rabbi
Yochanan amar me'hacha u'vata el hakohen asher yihyeh bayamim hahem. וכי תעלה
על דעתך שאדם הולך אצל הכהן שלא היה בימיו v'chi ta'aleh al
da'atcha she'adam holeich eitzel hakohen she'lo hayah beyamov? or he'll have at
those days. What other כהן Kohen are you going to go to?
אלא זה כשר ונתחלל. Ela zeh kasher venit-chalal.
So it means, okay, it turned out that that's who you had
even though he was a חלל, chalal, but nevertheless it's still good.
Okay, as long as you didn't know at the time and he
didn't know. But what...
does
the father of שמואל Shmuel is that giving honor to שמואל Shmuel
is that what...
No, he always called אבוה דשמואל, Avuha deShmuel, I'm not exactly sure
why. בעל מום דעבודה פסול מנלן? Ba'al mum de'avoda p'sul minlan? So
how do you know that doesn't apply to a בעל מום? ba'al
mum? So, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל דאמר קרא, Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel de’amar kra, the verse says לכן אמור הנני נותן לו
את בריתי שלום, Lachen emor hinni noten lo et briti shalom, by
again going back to פינחס. Pinchas. כשהוא שלם, K’shehu shalem, this idea
that it works for the זרע zera even if it's פסול pasul
even if it's חלל, chalal, that's only if he is שלום שלם,
shalom shalem, only if he is unblemished. ולא כשהוא חסר, V’lo keshu
chaser, not when he's lacking. והשלום... אה, והשלום כתיב? V’hashalom... ah, v’hashalom
ketiv? But it says שלום shalom not שלם. shalem. אמר רב נחמן
ו דשלום קטיעה היא. Amar Rav Nachman vav deShalom keti’a hi. No,
the ו vav is like not a full we there's a special
way we write the ו, vav, we don't write the full length
of the leg and that's to indicate that actually
to make that דרשה. drasha. You know, anyway, so anyway that's that
funny הלכה. halacha. I do have to tell you that I find
this I mean I don't I can't a) I just don't understand
the logic of it just from even a purely הלכתי halachic standpoint,
a חלל chalal doesn't have any קדושה, kedusha, a בעל מום ba'al
mum does, a בעל מום ba'al mum can't, you know, be מטמא
למתים, mitameh lemetim, can't marry the women a כהן Kohen can't marry,
a חלל chalal has none of those restrictions, a בעל מום ba'al
mum shares in the קרבנות korbanot we just read it in the
previous פרשה, parsha, right, that he's חלק כחלק יאכלו chelek kechelek yochelu
no, that was a different פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, but the פסוק pasuk
says that a בעל מום ba'al mum shares in the קרבנות korbanot
and obviously a בן גרושה ben grushah does not, and nevertheless when
it turns out that it was something you didn't discover that you
didn't know about, it's okay in one and not in the other.
The best I could say is similar to the גמרא's Gemara point
before about, you know, שרפין וסוטה, serafin vesotah, that in one case
it was discoverable and it was something that you know it was
not like this abstract knowledge thing, you know, it was actually something
that we could have, you know, that was like present to be
seen, so that somehow more marks it and we should have seen
it, you know, and that maybe more makes for the problem. But
I really find a hard time to understand this and particularly if
you, you know, to argue that like it's if if the argument
is that a מום mum is like somehow more of like less
ex- something more objectionable than the בן גרושה ben grushah, בן חלוצה,
Ben Chalutza. you know, that raises all these other issues that I
have. So anyway, questions that I have. Yes, Charles.
Two questions. Is that ו vav really not a full ו vav
in the our current ספרי תורה? Sifrei Torah? I think it's glossed
on that more than one.
What what is it, it looks like a י? yud?
It looks like a י. yud.
Well, it depends there's different ways of doing the ו קטיעה. vav
keti’a. Right.
There's some people read it with like a line between, right? Different
ways of doing it. You have a broken ו, vav, a
smaller like smaller all the way down to the ground.
Right, yeah.
And the ספר תורה Sefer Torah is still כשר. kosher.
Yeah, because that's the מסורה mesorah how to write it.
Okay, some second, more important or maybe more important question. This does
seem to have this debate which they don't seem to have fully
resolved would seem to have issues regarding a גר ger proving his
Jewish...
Right, so I've been translating it's a good question, I've been translating
אין דבר שבערוה פחות משנים ein davar shebe’erva pachos mishnayim as personal
status. There is some question about that and you're right and about
how to look at the whole like, you know, גר ger case
etc. and by גר ger to make the conversion take place, you
don't it's not you don't need two, you need three, you need
a בית דין. Beit Din. And then the question becomes right about
the issue you raised, exactly that about proving it. So that is
a good point. We do generally we basically rule like רבא Rava
against אביי, Abaye, which is a good thing, אין דבר שבערוה פחות
משנים ein davar shebe’erva pachos mishnayim even if in terms of proving
it because all the cases in the גמרא Gemara basically were to
invalidate people, okay, but it could also make a question about sometimes
it's in the flip. A woman needs to prove that she's divorced.
What level of proof does she need to produce that she's divorced?
Or somebody has to prove that they've converted, right? I mean so
these are, you know, so that's those are good questions. But we
basically פוסק pasken like רבא. Rava. Let's just start, let's just go
on. Let's get to the next משנה. Mishnah. Okay, כל מקום, kol
makom, let's start the next משנה. Mishnah. כל מקום שיש, Kol makom
sheyesh, כל מקום שיש קידושין ואין עבירה, kol makom sheyesh kiddushin ve’ein
aveira, הולד הולך... havelad holech...
now we're getting to the inter- the whole issue in קידושין kiddushin
about sta- about יחוס, yichus, about identity, you know, which is has
to do with like, you know, and all these פסולים psulim ממזר
mamzer and we just mentioned בן גרושה ben grusha בן חלוצה Ben
Chalutza, for כהן, Kohen, but, you know, all this question about what
is your... I there's got to be a word here, not identity
and not exactly status, but, you know, cl- somehow your your class,
what word would you use to describe questions like כהן לוי ישראל,
Kohen Levi Yisrael, ממזר? mamzer? Caste? Caste?
Genealogy? Status? Genealogy? Genealogy? We can use caste but it's a little
weird because it implies... yeah exactly. It really is like a caste.
We can say category?
Personal status category? Genealogy? All right, okay. Genealogical status, יחוס, yichus, let's
say יחוס. yichus. Anyway, okay. So anyway, let's take a look. Okay,
so כל מקום שיש קידושין ואין עבירה. kol makom sheyesh kiddushin ve’ein
aveira.
If if it's a mar- if it's two, you know, a man
and a woman and קידושין kiddushin is binding, if if there could
be קידושין kiddushin even if קידושין kiddushin didn't take place but it's
but legally there could be marriage between them. And there is no
sin that took place in their union, okay, which is hopefully a
standard case, הולד הולך אחר הזכר. havlad holeich achar hazachar.
So it's the status passes up is defined by the father, okay,
by the male of that pair. ואיזה, ve'eizeh, what would be a
scenario of this? זה כהנת לוייה וישראלית, ze Kohenet Leviya veYisraelit, whether
the woman is in either כהן לוי ישראלית, Kohen Levi Yisraelit, שנסת
לכהן לוי וישראל, sheniset leKohen Levi veYisrael, and the man is כהן
לוי וישראל. Kohen Levi veYisrael. So what's the status of the child?
Simple question. How what's the status of the child? It goes by
the status of the father. The status is a כהן Kohen the
kid's a כהן. Kohen. Status of the father is a לוי Levi
the kid's a לוי. Levi. It doesn't matter what the mother is,
it goes by the father. Okay, that's קידושין kiddushin is binding and
there was no עבירה. aveira. וכל מקום שיש קידושין ויש עבירה, vekol
makom sheyesh kiddushin veyesh aveira, now if קידושין kiddushin is binding but
it's in transgression, הולד הולך אחר הפגום, havlad holeich achar hapagum,
then the child goes by the invalidity, by the stigma, meaning it
doesn't matter mother or father, the stigma passes on to the child.
ואיזה, ve'eizeh, what would be that case? זו אלמנה לכהן גדול גרושה
וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט. zu almanah leKohen Gadol grushah vechalutzah leKohen Hedyot. First
of all, any of the forbidden כהן Kohen relationships, an אלמנה almanah
with a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol or גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט, grushah
vechalutzah leKohen Hedyot, there it's not actually the status, the kid doesn't
become a גרושה, grushah, but what we say is because it is
a forbidden union for a כהן, Kohen, the kid becomes a חלל,
chalal, okay, so that the kid gets affected either way, okay, but
then the idea as a concept of the stigma passes on, that's
more directly applicable to the next case. בת ישראל לממזר ולנתין. bat
Yisrael lemamzer ulenatin. I'm sorry, I skipped. ממזרת ונתינה לישראל, mamzeret venetinah
leYisrael, if the woman is a ממזר mamzer or נתין, natin, which
is the גבעונים Givonim and I'm not going to have a little
bracket the נתין natin for now, but let's just say ממזרת, mamzeret,
a woman is a ממזרת mamzeret who marries a male who is
not a ממזר mamzer or the reverse, a man is a ממזר
mamzer who marries a female who is not, okay, so ממזרת ונתינה
לישראל, mamzeret venetinah leYisrael, did I just say the same thing twice?
Anyway, fine. Okay, the woman is the ממזרת mamzeret and marries a
man who is not, or בת ישראל לממזר ונתין, bat Yisrael lemamzer
venatin, the woman is not a ממזר mamzer and she marries a
man who is, then the child is a ממזר. mamzer. Okay. So
marriage is binding because marriage is binding by the איסורי לאוין, issurei
lavin, if it's not כרת karet or מיתה, mitah, it's a binding
marriage if it's just a לאו, lav, okay, but nevertheless, the child
gets
the disqualified status. The child becomes a חלל chalal in the case
of כהנים kohanim and the child becomes a ממזר mamzer if one
of the parents is a ממזר. mamzer. Okay. וכל מי שאין לה
עליו קידושין אבל יש לה על אחרים קידושין, vekol mi she'ein lah
alav kiddushin aval yesh lah al acherim kiddushin, any woman for whom
קידושין kiddushin is not binding, אבל יש לה על אחרים קידושין, aval
yesh lah al acherim kiddushin, she could marry somebody else, she just
can't marry him.
יש לה עליו קידושין? yesh lah alav kiddushin?
יש לה על אחרים,
yesh
lah
al acherim,
other people can marry her, regarding her, other people can, whatever, it's
a funny construct, but anyway, other people can marry
her. Okay. הולד ממזר. havlad mamzer. This is the general point that
עריות, arayot, the child is a ממזר. mamzer. Now, ואיזהו, ve'eizehu, who
is this woman? Who what does it mean? Because ואיזהו, ve'eizehu, who
is this? זה הבא על אחת מכל העריות שבתורה. ze haba al
achat mikol ha'arayot shebaTorah. Either she's a married woman, okay, then other
people can marry her like her husband, okay, she's married to them,
or she's a sister, a mother, a daughter, and other people can
marry her. So basically means any woman who's, so who does it
exclude? Who's a woman that nobody could marry? Okay, so that is
the last case. וכל מי שאין לה לא עליו ולא על אחרים
קידושין, vekol mi she'ein lah lo alav velo al acherim kiddushin, any
woman who can't be married to anybody, הולד כמותה, havlad kemotah, the
child fathers the mother's status but is not a ממזר. mamzer. ואיזה,
ve'eizeh, זה ולד שפחה ונכרית. ze vlad shifcha venochrit. A non-Jewish woman
or a slave, right? There's no קידושין, kiddushin, I mean non-Jews have,
you know, בני נח, Bnei Noach, but for us as Jews, no
Jew can marry a woman who is not Jewish, no Jew can
marry a woman who is a slave. So therefore, in that case,
there's no קידושין, kiddushin, but nevertheless, the child isn't a ממזר, mamzer,
the child is either a non-Jew or a slave, depending on who
the mother is. And this is basically the principle of matrilineal descent.
Okay. So you're about to be, not today but soon, we're going
to actually be looking at the prime גמרא Gemara about the issue
of matrilineal descent. The father is Jewish and the mother isn't Jewish,
right, it goes by it goes that way, if it was the
reverse, right, if the mother was Jewish and the father was not,
either way it says, I mean that's not exactly covered in the
משנה, mishnah, but either way the principle is הולד כמותה, havlad kemotah,
okay.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagrees with this משנה mishnah
because he would say ממזר mamzer even by חייבי לאוין, chayavei lavin,
yes.
But it is covered, right, because she could be the קידושין kiddushin
was with someone else, but not not with.
Yeah,
but then but if we were to follow that logic we would
say that then it would be a ממזר, mamzer, which we don't
say, right. So it's because it's really the last part, until then
it was sort of balanced, men and women, the last part sort
of focused totally on the woman, right.
Yeah, because, yeah, because, is that really by the father, right?
Well, the first part says you go by the father, then it
says or you go by if there if קידושין kiddushin is binding
but it's an עבירה, aveira, you go by either parent, but then
it was describing the scenario equally from her perspective and his perspective.
In the end, it was totally from her perspective. If it's a
woman with whom קידושין kiddushin isn't binding but she can marry somebody
else, it's a ממזר. mamzer. If it's a woman with whom קידושין
kiddushin isn't binding and she can't marry somebody
else. It doesn't talk about the Jewish woman and the non-Jewish man
isn't like covered in the description of this משנה. Mishna. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. כל מקום שיש קידושין. Kol makom
sheyeish kiddushin. אמר ליה רבי שמעון לרבי יוחנן: Amar lei Rabbi Shimon
l'Rabbi Yochanan: כללה הוא? Klala hu? Does this real principle work? Now
we're going to have a fun thing and point out all the
things not in the משנה. Mishna. Okay, דכל מקום שיש קידושין ואין
עבירה הולד הולך אחר הזכר, d'kol makom sheyeish kiddushin v'ein aveira havlad
holeich achar hazachar, that whenever קידושין kiddushin is binding and there's no
transgression you follow the father? הרי גר, Harei ger, how about a
case of a convert שנסא ממזרת, shenasa mamzeret, who married a ממזרת,
mamzeret, because there's an opinion that by the—that the ממזרת mamzeret is
allowed to marry a גר. ger.
Okay, so is that halachically paskened? Yeah, that is the way we
פסקן. pasken. But it's a debate in the גמרא. Gemara. דיש קידושין
ואין עבירה, D'yeish kiddushin v'ein aveira, קידושין kiddushin is binding, there's no
sin, והולד הולך אחר הפגום, vehavlad holeich achar hapagum, and nevertheless even
when you do this, the child still is a ממזר, mamzer, which
is really unfortunate, or else it'd be a great way to solve
the ממזר mamzer problem, right? But we say the child follows. So
here's a case, no עבירה, aveira, and it doesn't go by the
father, it goes by which either whichever party is the ממזר, mamzer,
the child's the ממזר. mamzer. Doesn't matter about the father. דתניא, Detanya,
גר שנסא ממזרת, ger shenasa mamzeret, if a גר ger marries a
woman who is a ממזרת, mamzeret, הולד ממזר. havlad mamzer. You don't
go by the father. The child's a ממזר, mamzer, it always goes
by the ממזר mamzer status. דברי רבי יוסי. Divrei Rabbi Yosei. That's
what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he
said, so that doesn't sit in our משנה. Mishna. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so who
is this—so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said back to רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, or so אמר ליה amar lei he said back to him,
מי סברת מתניתין רבי יוסי היא? mi seivart matnitin Rabbi Yosei hi?
Who says our משנה Mishna is רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yosei? מתניתין רבי
יהודה היא, Matnitin Rabbi Yehuda hi, maybe it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
who disagrees with רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosei. What does רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda say? דאמר, d'amar, גר לא ישא ממזרת, ger lo yisa mamzeret,
a גר ger is not allowed to marry a ממזרת. mamzeret. So
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda fundamental argument with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei is
not about the status of the child, it's about whether a גר
ger is allowed to marry a ממזרת mamzeret or not. So he
says a גר ger is not allowed to marry a ממזרת. mamzeret.
And then it fits the categories because if that marriage was forbidden,
the child goes by the invalidity, goes by the stigma. Okay, ויש
קידושין ויש עבירה, veyeish kiddushin veyeish aveira, so according to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, it is in transgression, and once it's in transgression, it
completely fits our משנה. Mishna. הולד הולך אחר הפגום, Havlad holeich achar
hapagum, then it goes by the stigma. Okay, so that fits our
כלל. klal. But we're going to have a problem now with everything
that wasn't mentioned in the משנה. Mishna. Either it's an exception and
the משנה's Mishna כלל klal isn't right, or if it's not an
exception, why wasn't it included in the examples? Okay, so we're not
going to be happy either way. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says
fine, you're telling me that that case fits, ממזר mamzer and a
גר ger according to the opinion that that's forbidden, the child is
a ממזר, mamzer, why wasn't that listed as an example? So the
גמרא Gemara says וניתיני, uniteinei, for list it. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says no, תנא כל מקום לאתויי. tanna kol makom l'atuyei. That's
why it has a general statement, כל
מקום, kol makom, right? It says כל מקום, kol makom, if you
take a look, it starts by saying כל מקום שיש קידושין ואין
עבירה, kol makom sheyeish kiddushin v'ein aveira, and then it has כל
מקום שיש קידושין ויש עבירה. kol makom sheyeish kiddushin veyeish aveira. So
the כל מקום kol makom of יש קידושין ויש עבירה yeish kiddushin
veyeish aveira includes the case of a ממזר mamzer and a גר.
ger. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it eima, לעולם רבי יוסי, le'olam Rabbi Yosei,
or you know what, let's go back. We could go like רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yosei. And we could say it is an exception. Okay,
there is an exception to the rule.
ואיזו זו. ve'eizo zu.
I well that's exactly, thanks, it's exactly where we're going to get
to. Okay, it is רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei, you're right, it is
an exception. Okay, so how do I deal with the fact that
there's an exception to the rule, that there could be a case
of no עבירה aveira and the kid still carries the stigma? Because
as Michael said, ותנא ואיזו זו vetanna ve'eizo zu למעוטי, l'ma'utei, because
ואיזו זו ve'eizo zu is telling you this כלל klal does not
totally true. Here is the list that it applies to. It's not
you can't assume that this rule applies to everything. Okay, so basically
what we're going to do is, okay, we're going to have to
start adding cases and decide which thing, okay, so we've got כל
מקום, kol makom, you know, אין עבירה, ein aveira, I'll just put
that up, right? It goes by the זכר, zachar, it goes by
the man, and we basically have, you know, כהן לוי ישראל kohein
levi yisrael cases, okay. And then
but then what we're going to say is,
you know,
ואיזו, ve'eizo, I'm trying to figure out how to draw this on
the board. Anyway, first we have this, we have the ואיזו
זו, ve'eizo zu, the גמרא's Gemara going to say ואיזו זו ve'eizo
zu means since I'm giving the list, it means there are some
exceptions. That's what the גמרא's Gemara going to assume, right? Here's the
כלל, klal, here's the list. The list indicates what are the exceptions.
So here we're going to have here are going to be the
exceptions indicated by the word ואיזו זו. ve'eizo zu. And the כל
מקום kol makom was the כלל klal and that's going to allow
us to say other things that should have been on the list
we didn't mention. Well, that's the כלל klal is coming to tell
us. ואיזו זו ve'eizo zu allows us to say it's it's not
everything and there are some exceptions.
I thought ואיזו זו ve'eizo zu is defining the כלל. klal.
Meaning no, the גמרא's Gemara going to play it both ways. Here's
a general rule. It's like כלל ופרט. klal u'prat. Which one in
the end dictate? So the גמרא's Gemara going to get to play
it both ways because I understand, but this is the משנה. Mishna.
Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara going to get to play it both
ways because the משנה's... Mishna does not list all cases. There are
other cases that should have been included as a good application of
the rule, and there are other cases that are an exception to
the rule. And we're going to have to deal with the fact
that none of those are in the משנה. Mishna. So what we're
basically going to wind up saying is, anything that fits the rule,
we're going to say it was included in the כלל, klal, כל
מקום. kol makom. Anything that's an exception to the rule, we're going
to say because it said איזו זו, eizo zo, which was saying
no, it's only—here's the application, means there's some things that are exceptions
to the rules. Okay? So we're going to use those phrases to
deal with everything that's not in the משנה. Mishna. Okay, and by
the way, we're going to apply it to the end part, כל
מקום שיש עבירה, kol makom sheyesh aveira, because הולך אחר הפגם, holech
achar hapgam, okay? Right? That's what the second part said. ואיזו זו,
ve'eizo zo, right? ואיזו זו. ve'eizo zo. So it has it here
too. Okay, rule, exception.
Okay, so now, okay, this is where it goes by the זכר,
zachar, and this is where it goes by the פגם. pgam. Okay,
so now, because each one says here's the rule and here's the
list, it's going to allow us to put missing things in either
of those categories. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, so where does
the issue of what do you call it, סגי, sagi, about a
גר ger and ממזרת, mamzeret, okay, so גר ger and ממזרת, mamzeret,
where does גר ger and ממזרת mamzeret go? So either גר ger
and ממזרת mamzeret get added here, because they apply to the rule
of go after the פגם pgam if there's an עבירה, aveira, that's
according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Or if there's no עבירה, aveira,
then they're an exception to the rule, and they go under here,
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, גר ger and ממזרת, mamzeret, because they're an
exception to the rule. No עבירה aveira and it still goes by
the פגם. pgam. You see what we're doing? Yes? I'm not asking
if you're happy with it, but you see what we're saying. Okay.
Alright. Anyway. ותו לא, v'tu lo, so now that's going to be
the rest of this דף. daf. Basically saying everything not listed either
works with the rule or is an exception and it fits into
one of these, one of these phrases.
Okay, ותו לא v'tu lo is nothing else, והרי חלל שנשא בת
ישראל. vaharei chalal shenasa bat Yisrael. A חלל chalal married a בת
ישראל. bat Yisrael. דיש קידושין ואין עבירה. de'yesh kiddushin ve'ein aveira. Now
the גמרא Gemara is primarily looking to find exceptions, obviously that's more
interesting. Okay, a חלל chalal marries a בת ישראל, bat Yisrael, that
קידושין kiddushin is binding, there's no עבירה aveira for a חלל chalal
כהן kohen to marry a non-כהן kohen woman. Okay, it's totally מותר,
muttar, קידושין kiddushin is binding, and והולד הולך אחר הזכר. ve'havlad holech
achar hazachar. And the child go—oh no, actually this isn't an exception.
This is actually the rule. Okay. And the child follows the father.
Okay wait, what's the problem here?
חלל
שנשא בת
ישראל
דיש קידושין ואין עבירה והולד הולך אחר הזכר.
chalal shenasa bat Yisrael de'yesh kiddushin ve'ein
aveira havlad holech achar hazachar.
Yeah. And why is that a problem? That actually fits. It's just
a problem that it's not listed.
It's against רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi because he's saying all of the
things should be listed, ואיזו זו. ve'eizo zo. Right?
No, we're just saying the one exception falls into the ואיזו זו.
ve'eizo zo.
Oh, I guess that's, yeah.
Saying ואיזו זו ve'eizo zo is to confine it to just those
things listed.
Oh, I see your point. That now we're assuming, because I already
jumped ahead where the גמרא Gemara is going to use all the
categories, but you're saying, I see your point, you're saying at this
stage we're assuming ואיזו זו, ve'eizo zo, you're, I think you're right,
I think you're right. Okay, so I jumped ahead to assume we're
going to use all of the categories to deal with all the
problems, but I think Jenna is correct that the גמרא Gemara at
this stage is assuming that ואיזו זו ve'eizo zo means it's only
these things that are listed, and we're not looking at the כלל
klal according to רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. So if it's only these
things that are listed, that are the application, here's another application of
the rule. Okay, yeah, thank you, that's right. ותו לא, v'tu lo,
are you telling me it's only these things that are listed that
are the application of the rule?
והרי חלל שנשא בת ישראל דיש קידושין ואין עבירה והולד הולך אחר
הזכר vaharei chalal shenasa bat Yisrael de'yesh kiddushin ve'ein aveira havlad holech
achar hazachar and inherits the father's status. So ואיזו זו, ve'eizo zo,
it's not a complete list. You're right, right, it's not a complete
list. So
גמרא Gemara says הא לא קשיא. ha lo kashya. That's not a
problem. כדוסתאי בן רבי יהודה. kedostai ben Rabbi Yehuda. Like כדוסתאי בן
רבי יהודה. Dostai ben Rabbi Yehuda. it doesn't follow the father and
the ואיזו זו ve'eizo zo is a complete list. סבירא ליה. svira
lei. Okay, so now your, yeah, Genack's right. Now at this stage,
I jumped too far ahead. At this stage, we're asserting that the
ואיזו זו ve'eizo zo means there are exceptions, and ואיזו זו ve'eizo
zo is telling you it's only this list and nothing else is
an application of the rule. So the גמרא gemara says, והרי ישראל
שנשא חללה, ve'harei Yisrael shenasa challala, one minute. How about a ישראל
Yisrael who married a woman who's a חללה, challala, which is permissible,
he's not a כהן. kohen. דיש קידושין ואין עבירה, de'yesh kiddushin ve'ein
aveira, הולד הולך אחר הזכר havalad holech achar hazachar and the child
is not a חלל. challal. The child is כשר. kasher. Okay, 'cause
he's a ישראל. Yisrael. ישראל Yisrael married a חללה, challala, the child
is a חללה, challala, the child is כשר. kasher. So that's a
case where it goes by the male, so how can you say,
yeah, how can you say ואיזו זו ve'eizo zo is the entire
application of the list? Okay. So the גמרא gemara says, תנא, tanna,
now he said what I was jumping ahead of, כל מקום דרישא
לאתויי. kol makom de'reisha le'atuyei. Fine, the כל מקום דרישא kol makom
de'reisha allows us to both deal with things that are applications not
included and to deal with exceptions. Okay, so the כל מקום kol
makom now of the רישא, reisha, right? The כל מקום kol makom
of the רישא reisha is going to include what? So this, so
the exception is גר וממזרת. ger u'mamzeret. That's a case where there
is no עבירה aveira and it goes by the פסול. psul. And
the case that's not listed that should have been here is ישראל
וחללה, Yisrael ve'challala, or we can now also include חלל וישראלית, challal
ve'Yisraelit, right, where, where in those types of cases, no עבירה aveira
and the child actually would go by the father. Okay, so those
are other applications of the rule, right? So we were starting that
it was correct assuming that there's only, you know, there're no more
applications of the rule, everything else is an exception. And now we're
saying actually there's some things that are applications we didn't include and
there're some exceptions. Applications we didn't include, no עבירה aveira and it
goes by the father is the חלל challal situation. Not, it always
goes by the father.
Not that. Who says?
Not like רב דוסתי. Rav Dostai. I know, but once we give
this answer we don't have to say that. We always go by
the father. No עבירה, aveira, we go by the father. There are
cases, no עבירה, aveira, we go by the פסול. psul. That's the
גר וממזרת. ger u'mamzeret. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says like
this, וניתנייה בהדיא. u'nitneia be'hedya.
You say you go by the father, חלל וישראלית, challal ve'Yisraelit, and
the kid would be
כשר לכהונה?
kasher le'kehuna? If it's a חלל
וישראלית... challal ve'Yisraelit...
What do you mean? You listed חלל וישראלית. challal ve'Yisraelit. Right. והולד
הולך אחר הזכר, ve'havalad holech achar hazachar, right, so he'd be a
חלל. challal. Yeah. And ישראל וחללה, Yisrael ve'challala,
the ולד velad would be כשר. kasher.
Right. Okay, so גמרא gemara says וניתנייה בהדיא. u'nitneia be'hedya. So if
there are things that are included in the list, I get that
you don't want to list exceptions. You want to try to create
a כלל. klal. But why not say more of the applications explicitly?
Okay, why not say them explicitly? משום דלא פסיקא ליה mishum de'lo
pasika lei because you can't say it easily in the way the
משנה mishna is phrased. היכי ניתני? heichi nitnei? How should you say
it? כהנת לוי וישראלית וחללה שנסא לכהן ולוי
וישראל. kohenet levi ve'Yisraelit ve'challala shenasa le'kohen ve'levi ve'Yisrael.
Okay, that's how you'd want to say it, right, if you wanted
to include the חלל challal in that. But you can't frame it
that way because then you're including the possibility that a חללה challala
could marry a כהן. kohen. וחללה לכהן לא חזיא. ve'challala le'kohen lo
chazya. It doesn't fit neatly in the framing of the משנה, mishna,
which is a pretty good answer. Okay. So in the case of
כהן לוי ישראל, kohen levi Yisrael, we could have included a חלל
challal with a ישראלית Yisraelit or a חללה challala I mean with
a ישראלית Yisraelit or a חללה challala with a ישראל, Yisrael, but
it wouldn't have been easy to fit that into the משנה mishna
in one sentence. You'd have to make a... in one sentence. Okay,
we want to make a tight little teaching of the משנה. mishna.
Okay. So now we've allowed for the fact that there are things
that are part of the כלל klal we didn't list and there
are exceptions to the כלל. klal. והאיכא דרבה בר בר חנה. ve'ha'ika
de'Rabba bar bar Chana. How about רבה בר בר חנה? Rabba bar
bar Chana? דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, de'amar Rabba
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, מצרי שני שנשא מצרית ראשונה בנה
שלישי הוי. Mitzri sheini shenasa Mitzrit rishona bena shelishi havei. Okay,
so the הלכה halacha is that a מצרי Mitzri until the third
generation, a מצרי Mitzri converts, that's he's a first generation or she.
His child or her child is a second generation מצרי. Mitzri. Only
a third generation, דור שלישי יבוא להם בקהל השם. dor shelishi yavo
lahem bikhal Hashem. Now how do you count generations? Let's say you
have a first generation מצרי, Mitzri, right, I'm sorry, a second generation
מצרי Mitzri marrying a man, marrying a first generation מצרית. Mitzrit. Is
the child a third generation or a second generation? Got the question?
Okay, so ההוא hahu says, מצרי שני שנשא מצרית ראשונה בנה שלישי
הוי. Mitzri sheini shenasa Mitzrit rishona bena shelishi havei.
The child goes by the father presumably and it's a third generation.
So there you have a case of it's מותר mutar for a
מצרי Mitzri to marry a מצרי. Mitzri. They're all converts here. Okay.
It's מותר mutar for them to marry one another and והולד הולך
אחר הזכר. ve'havalad holech achar hazachar.
The generations are counted based on the father. So that's another application
of this rule of מצרי Mitzri and מצרית Mitzrit that we should
go by the father. Why was that not listed? So the גמרא
gemara say, you know what? הא תנא כל מקום דרישא לאתויי. ha
tanna kol makom de'reisha le'atuyei. Fine, that's what the כל מקום kol
makom is doing. We're now allowing ourselves... the generations are counted based
on the father. So that's another application of this rule of מצרי
Mitzri and מצרית, Mitzrit, that we should go by the father. Why
was that not listed? So the גמרא Gemara says, you know what?
הוי תנא כל מקום לדרשא לאתויי. Havi tanna kol makom ledrasha le'atuyei.
Fine. That's what the כל מקום kol makom is doing. We now
we're allowing ourselves to say anything that wasn't listed is included in
the כל מקום. kol makom. You're right, that's another application of the
rules. Okay, ולרב דימי דאמר שני הוי, u-l'Rav Dimi d'amar sheni havi,
how about רב דימי Rav Dimi that says the opposite? You go
by the mother in the case of מצרי Mitzri and מצרית. Mitzrit.
So,
getting what's the answer? תנא איזהו לאתויי. Tanna eizehu l'atuyei. Okay,
so according to some that would be it's either the rule or
the exception. So now it's perfect. Anything that's a rule that we
didn't list is included in כל מקום. kol makom. Anything that's an
exception that we didn't list is included in איזהו. eizehu.
Well, the rule is still generally true, but yes, I know. The
best thing is to do, is there's two parts. One is the
literary question of it doesn't fit. The other question is the legal
question, is this rule at all helpful? So if we can make
the exceptions as narrow as possible then we can tolerate some exceptions
if the rule is generally true. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. ואיכא, ve-ika, what about the case of כי אתא
רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, באומות הלך
אחר הזכר? be-umot halach achar hazachar?
If you have two non non-Jew and the case we're going to
see is a כנעני Kena'ani and a non-כנעני, Kena'ani, right? So, and
what would you consider the child? You know, what tribe would the
child be? Would it be a כנעני Kena'ani and the הלכה's halacha
about כנענים, Kena'anim, you know, or would it be a non? So
no, you go by the father. Okay, that's fine. נתגיירו, nitgayeru, now
let's say they've converted. Okay, and you have to decide the status
of the child. It could also be a מואבי Moavi and an
אדומי Edomi where there are different הלכות halachot about whether when you
can marry into them, right? Even after they've converted. So he says,
הלך אחר הפגום שבשניהם. halach achar hapagum shebishneihem. So you go by
the פגום. pagum. Now, if you have a converted אדומי Edomi marrying
a converted מצרי, Mitzri, it's אין עבירה יש קידושין, ein aveira yesh
kiddushin, it's like מצרי Mitzri and מצרית, Mitzrit, אין עבירה יש קידושין,
ein aveira yesh kiddushin, they both converted. And it says you go
by the פגום. pagum. So that's an exception to the rule, right?
אין עבירה יש קידושין ein aveira yesh kiddushin and you're going by
the פגום. pagum.
Well, okay, so the גמרא Gemara will say because if one of
them has a more disqualifying status. Okay, we'll see it in the
גמרא. Gemara. But it would be a case where one of them
has a more disqualifying status of the other. Right, exactly, exactly. So
we'll see it in the גמרא. Gemara. So you go by the
most disqualifying status of the two. So that's an exception to the
rule. So the גמרא Gemara says, תנא איזהו לאתויי. Tanna eizehu l'atuyei.
Fine.
So here not only is an exception possibly מצרי Mitzri and מצרית
Mitzrit but it's also a case about אומות שנתגיירו. umot shenitgayeru. Okay,
and we'll see that case. שנתגיירו shenitgayeru and in those cases you
go by the פגום. pagum. Okay, so yes. And notice by the
way, and this actually gets back to Jenna's question, all of the
exceptions are cases where we're not talking about naturally born Jews, right?
At least one of them, right? Either גר ממזר ger mamzer you
go by the פגום pagum or two nations that converted, אדומי Edomi
and מצרי Mitzri or whatever, you go by the פגום. pagum. So
this still holds true, right? By like naturally born Jews. I mean
מצרי Mitzri and מצרית Mitzrit is the question about which category you
put it in. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this. היי מאי,
Hai mai, one minute says the גמרא, Gemara, how can you do
all of this? אי אמרת בשלמא מתניתין רבי יהודה היא, ei amrat
bishlama matnitin Rabbi Yehuda hi, if our משנה mishnah is רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda by the מצרי Mitzri and by the גר ger and
the ממזר, mamzer, כל מקום דרישא לאתויי ישראל שנשא חללה. kol makom
deriesha l'atuyei Yisrael shenasa chalala. So the כל מקום kol makom here
includes the חללה chalala case. Okay, דרבא בר בר חנה. deRabba Bar
Bar Chana. And it could also include the רבא בר בר חנה
Rabba Bar Bar Chana of the מצרי Mitzri and the מצרית Mitzrit
case. Okay, now we're going to go through like does something fit
into each box? Now that we've established that there are things that
each box creates more things in the category and allows for exceptions.
Okay, so if you say this as this and this
as this, איזהו לאתויי דרב דימי ודרבי, eizehu l'atuyei deRav Dimi u-deRavi,
איזהו eizehu is either because now we're working with רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. איזהו eizehu is coming to deal with the exception to the
rule of the אומות שנתגיירו umot shenitgayeru and possibly the מצרי Mitzri
and the מצרית Mitzrit depending on how you פוסקין. pasken. So we
have things that fall into the exception category. Okay.
People sort of following the thrust of
this? כל מקום דסיפא לאתויי גר שנשא ממזרת, kol makom desifa l'atuyei
ger shenasa mamzeret, and the כל מקום kol makom here we're dealing
with רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so here there is something that's an
application that's not included. גר וממזרת ger u-mamzeret according to him is
an עבירה aveira and it goes by the פגום. pagum. Okay. So
we've got all these categories accounted for, except not that one. We've
all these categories accounted for. He says, but אלא אי אמרת רבי
יוסי היא, ela ei amrat Rabbi Yosi hi, but according to רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi then not all the boxes are filled. כל מקום
דרישא כדאמרן, kol makom deriesha k'demaran, the כל מקום kol makom here
includes the ישראל Yisrael and the חללה chalala and maybe the מצרי
Mitzri and the מצרית Mitzrit case. That's another application of going by
the male. איזהו eizehu the exception כדאמרן. k'demaran. First of all, it's
רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yosi's idea that the exception גר וממזרת ger u-mamzeret
it goes by the פגום pagum and all of the אומות שנתגיירו.
umot shenitgayeru. All of those are the exception that you go by
the פגום. pagum. אלא כל מקום דסיפא לאתויי מאי, ela kol makom
desifa l'atuyei mai, but there's nothing in the סיפא seifa of when
there's an עבירה aveira you go by the פגום pagum that's not
mentioned. So there's nothing else included in the כלל klal that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has what we're assuming the כל kol is coming
to include. Yeah, that's what we're assuming. We're going to answer that.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda includes in that כל, kol, גר וממזרת, ger
umamzeret, it's an עבירה aveira and you go by the פגם, pegam,
but for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose he doesn't פסקן pasken that way.
So the גמרא Gemara says you haven't brought anything else in this
box. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay let's see, the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, וטעמייך, ve-ta'amayikh, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, איזו זו דסיפא
למה לי? eizo zo de-seifa lama li? You don't need something in
every box, says the גמרא. Gemara. You don't have an exception here
for right to the הלכה halacha of going after the פגם pegam
when there's an עבירה. aveira. אלא איידי דתנא רישא איזו זו, ela
ayidi de-tana reisha eizo zo, תני סיפא איזו זו. tani seifa eizo
zo. Of course you have those boxes in the first half of
the משנה Mishna where we did have more things to include and
things to exclude. We have those boxes in the end. So הכי
נמי איידי דתנא רישא כל מקום, hachi nami ayidi de-tana reisha kol
makom, תנא סיפא כל מקום. tana seifa kol makom. Okay, יישר כח.
shkoiyach. Alright, that was a little exhausting. Let's try to do, we'll
see if we can get in two more minutes, one more case.
גופא, gufa, כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, ki ata Ravin amar
Rabbi Yochanan, באומות הלך אחר הזכר, be-umot halech achar hazachar, נתגיירו הלך
אחר פגום שבשניהם. nitgayeru halech achar pagum she-be-shneihem. מאי באומות הלך אחר
הזכר? mai be-umot halech achar hazachar? What would be the case that
they're non-Jews, they remain non-Jews, and the tribe is defined by the
father, right? כדתניא, ke-de-tanya, מנין לאחד מן האומות שבא על כנענית, minayin
le-echad min ha-umot she-ba al Kena'anit, a female כנענית, Kena'anit, you know,
has a child with somebody from not one of the seven
nations, והוליד בן, ve-holid ben, שאתה רשאי לקנותו בעבד? she-ata rashai liknoto
be-eved? How do you know that that child of that kid, that
kid is not considered to be a כנעני Kena'ani and you'd be
allowed to have them as a slave and it's not under the
מצוה mitzvah of destroying all the seven כנעני Kena'ani nations that you're
not allowed to own them as slaves etc.? How do you know
that child is not one of the כנעני Kena'ani nations if the
father is not a כנעני? Kena'ani? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: וגם מבני
התושבים הגרים עמכם, ve-gam mi-benei ha-toshavim ha-garim imachem, from those that are
not, those that are dwelling in your land, they're not native to
your land, מהם תקנו, me-hem tiknu, you can actually still buy those
children as slaves. Okay, so if they're not native, if they're not
native כנענים, Kena'anim, they're just dwelling in your land, which is understood
to be the definition of native or not native where we're like
sort of a little bit making reading our assumptions into the פסוק.
pasuk. We're assuming what defines that is the father. So if the
person is not native, meaning if the father isn't native, but they're
in the land and they have a wife who's a כנענית, Kena'anit,
the child is not a כנעני. Kena'ani. יכול אף עבד, yachol af
eved, or maybe it would be כנעני, Kena'ani, שבא על שפחה מן
האומות she-ba al shifcha min ha-umot והוליד בן, ve-holid ben, שאתה רשאי
לקנותו בעבד? she-ata rashai liknoto be-eved? What about the reverse? If it
was a כנעני Kena'ani man who had a child with a non-כנענית
Kena'anit woman? Maybe that child you'd be allowed to purchase, would not
be considered a כנעני? Kena'ani? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: אשר הולידו בארצכם.
asher holidu be-artzechem. You can buy these slaves from those that are
born in your land, meaning that by haphazardly they're born in your
land, that's not really their identity. Their real identity is that they
live somewhere else or their father lives somewhere else. מן הנולדים בארצכם,
min ha-noladim be-artzechem, those you can, אבל לא מן הגרים בארצכם, aval
lo min ha-garim be-artzechem, those that live the land, defined by the
father. If the father is he is from כנען, Kena'an, so the
children are basically considered to be living in כנען Kena'an because they
follow the father. So in that case, you know, it goes by
the father. Of course, you realize what we did is we took
our assumptions, we read into the פסוק pasuk and then we read
it back out of the פסוק, pasuk, right? Because the פסוק pasuk
doesn't say anything about father. Whether it just says there are some
people that are, sometimes they're considered to be, you know, born abroad
but living here and sometimes they're born here but they're living abroad.
And who is that? Well, it goes by the father. So you
see you go by the father. Anyway, so for the non-Jewish nations,
for for the non-Jews, the status of which nation you're part of
is defined by the father and we'll continue tomorrow about what happens
when they convert and you deal with an אדומי Edomi convert and
a מואבי Moavi convert or an עמוני Ammoni convert and how that
works out.